<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>musings about silly things</title>
    <link>http://heiber.im/</link>
    <description>Recent content on musings about silly things</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <managingEditor>hello@heiber.im (Moritz Heiber)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>hello@heiber.im (Moritz Heiber)</webMaster>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 11 Jun 2015 07:55:54 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="http://heiber.im/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>My thoughts on the Fitbit One</title>
      <link>http://heiber.im/post/my_thoughts_on_the_fitbit_one/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jun 2015 07:55:54 +0200</pubDate>
      <author>hello@heiber.im (Moritz Heiber)</author>
      <guid>http://heiber.im/post/my_thoughts_on_the_fitbit_one/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Like pretty much anyone interested in technology I was curious from the very beginning what body or fitness trackers can provide of value to our every day lives at this point in time. The ability to accurately judge your level of fitness and what to do about staying healthy is something I&amp;rsquo;d truly appreciate. I&amp;rsquo;ve been struggling with my body weight since I was a small child and still struggling with staying healthy, positive and depression free to this very date.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next chapter recounts my experience using the Fitbit One for three weeks. And while I also purchased a Jawbone UP2, I won&amp;rsquo;t give an account of its performance here since it didn&amp;rsquo;t do any better than the One, in fact, it performed considerably worse in most categories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h1 id=&#34;fitbit-one:6d68888f96fe63e8931dde6f6aa7577b&#34;&gt;Fitbit One&lt;/h1&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I mainly purchased the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.fitbit.com/one&#34;&gt;Fitbit One&lt;/a&gt; to help me with the seemingly never-ending quest of losing/keeping weight, staying in good health and also to maybe improve my sleeping habits. I turned to the One for a couple of of reasons:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I sweat&lt;/strong&gt;. A lot at times. Especially when I&amp;rsquo;m at practice/working out. It&amp;rsquo;s just something I&amp;rsquo;ve come to terms with. It used to be worse, back when I still had 20+ pounds more to carry around with me, but it&amp;rsquo;s still noticeably different from other people working out barely breaking a sweat. The One is a simple tracker you fix to your clothing, it&amp;rsquo;s sweat resistant, and thus ideal for me to work out with. A bracelet would probably be itching after half a day or two without taking it off in between (which is not what I&amp;rsquo;m after) with all the sweat and grease accumulating under its band. Furthermore, pretty much any of these straps are said to cause allergic skin reactions at some point time (which my family, myself to a lesser extend, are prone to).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;I like the prospect of being woken up lightly&lt;/strong&gt;. And without disturbing the sleep of my significant other. The discrete vibrations the One is giving off is good enough for getting me up in the morning. I was torn at first, still keeping my iPhone&amp;rsquo;s alarm set for a comfortable time, but I&amp;rsquo;ve done away with it. The One&amp;rsquo;s good enough.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.tomsguide.com/us/heart-rate-monitor,review-2885.html&#34;&gt;Heartbeat enabled wrist trackers are a sham&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;. There, I&amp;rsquo;ve set it. Yes, and even your beloved Apple Watch is barely accurate at judging your pulse/activity. It still takes professional equipment (read: a proper heart rate sensor strapped to your chest) to measure your workouts accurately. I&amp;rsquo;m not paying extra for technology that barely works as advertised.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For keeping track of my meals, I also connected it to &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.myfitnesspal.com/&#34;&gt;MyFitnessPal&lt;/a&gt; to let the One know about my calorie intake and my weight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then started wearing it tucked away in my trousers&amp;rsquo; pockets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-liked-about-it:6d68888f96fe63e8931dde6f6aa7577b&#34;&gt;What I liked about it&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Accuracy&lt;/strong&gt;: I never had the impression that the One wasn&amp;rsquo;t up to the task of measuring what it&amp;rsquo;s meant to be measuring accurately. That is, steps and floors climbed. Anything else it needs to extrapolate from the limited data it&amp;rsquo;s getting.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Size, weight&lt;/strong&gt;: For me, these tracker will have to be hardly noticeable to wear them comfortably. The One is tiny, you can basically stick anywhere on your body (except for your limbs) and it&amp;rsquo;ll work reliably.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Battery life&lt;/strong&gt;: While some appreciate getting through the day on a single charge while using their mobile phone I&amp;rsquo;m continuously baffled by lack of juice most wireless appliances carry around these days. The One comes with at least 5 - 7 days of battery power, well enough to get me through a week. And it&amp;rsquo;s charger is micro USB, just like your phone&amp;rsquo;s, which makes it a good travel companion.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Software/dashboard/app&lt;/strong&gt;: Fitbit did a great job at their online software functionality. Their website has a dashboard with your most important data that you may adjust and rearrange to your liking. Consequently, the mobile app (tested on iOS) you&amp;rsquo;re using on a day-to-day basis is just as beautiful and easy to use. I hardly felt at home so quickly with any other connected app before. It&amp;rsquo;s also modestly good at visualizing your daily/weekly goals, although I sort of missed reminders or encouragement throughout the day.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Silent wake-up calls&lt;/strong&gt;: The One is able to wake you silently at a time of your choosing. It doesn&amp;rsquo;t do any &amp;ldquo;smart&amp;rdquo; alarms (i.e. wake you up according to your sleep cycle) but I found the feature to work sufficiently well and didn&amp;rsquo;t miss any of the features other manufactures are tooting for their product line.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-didn-t-like:6d68888f96fe63e8931dde6f6aa7577b&#34;&gt;What I didn&amp;rsquo;t like&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Activity tracking&lt;/strong&gt;: So, as I mentioned, the one&amp;rsquo;s good at tracking your steps and the amount of floors traversed each day. It really sucks at tracking pretty much anything else though. Riding your bike? Out of luck, the One doesn&amp;rsquo;t know about it. Going for a run? Better make sure you tell the One that you&amp;rsquo;re going for a run. Going to sleep? Push the right button and &lt;strong&gt;put it in a sleeve you have to wear throughout the whole night&lt;/strong&gt;. Just the sleeve itself is infuriating at times, since it clearly is exposed to a lot of tear and wear after just a couple of nights.
But the sleep tracking is also lacking in granularity severely, and it doesn&amp;rsquo;t figure out when you&amp;rsquo;re going to sleep and have woken up automatically, &lt;strong&gt;despite setting the alarm&lt;/strong&gt;. The fact that you constantly have to think about &amp;ldquo;Do I need to tell it what I&amp;rsquo;m doing right now?&amp;rdquo; is really distracting and I just couldn&amp;rsquo;t figure at times why the One wasn&amp;rsquo;t able to gather enough data to guess what I&amp;rsquo;m doing at the specific moment in time. A serious flaw to me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Water resistence&lt;/strong&gt;: &amp;ldquo;Splash proof&amp;rdquo; just doesn&amp;rsquo;t cut it for something that is supposed to be tracking all my activities throughout the day. Plus, the design of the One could&amp;rsquo;ve allowed for a tighter, more resistant casing. Why Fitbit didn&amp;rsquo;t go for that obvious advantage is beyond me.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Calorie burn&lt;/strong&gt;: This is largely based on the steps you take and the floors you climb throughout the day. Therefore, it&amp;rsquo;s horrendously off in precisely the situations you actually want it to be accurate: When you exercise, i.e. actually trying to change your life for the better. While running would be accounted for semi-accurately, others like lifting weights, boxing or swimming would be out of the question. Either the One&amp;rsquo;s count is awfully off or you&amp;rsquo;re not able to track the activity at all.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Product cycle&lt;/strong&gt;: The One&amp;rsquo;s been on the market for almost 3 years. It&amp;rsquo;s save to say Fitbit isn&amp;rsquo;t going to invest a lot of time into improving a product that&amp;rsquo;s 3 years old. In a market that changing as rapidly as the tracker landscape that&amp;rsquo;s not really an option and I reckon the One is going to (or as some might argue, already does) suffer from the same level of negligence as its sister product, the Aria smart scale, does.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;what-i-ended-up-doing:6d68888f96fe63e8931dde6f6aa7577b&#34;&gt;What I ended up doing&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, I sent it back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All in all I couldn&amp;rsquo;t shake the feeling of using inadequate technology for a task it never was meant to cover. I&amp;rsquo;d love to get technology that helps me live a healthier life, but I&amp;rsquo;m afraid the current standard isn&amp;rsquo;t quite there yet. It&amp;rsquo;s probably going to take at least another year until it&amp;rsquo;s viable enough.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Also, all of these trackers do not come in cheap, the One is available from 95€, it&amp;rsquo;s fiercest competitor, the Jawbone UP2, costs upwards of 120€. That&amp;rsquo;s not exactly pocket change, at least not for me. Which puts a heavier emphasize on my last argument.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was worth a try, but for now I&amp;rsquo;m as well off without a fitness tracker than I am with one.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Switching to Hugo</title>
      <link>http://heiber.im/post/switching-to-hugo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2015 20:12:10 +0200</pubDate>
      <author>hello@heiber.im (Moritz Heiber)</author>
      <guid>http://heiber.im/post/switching-to-hugo/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://gohugo.io&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt; is a static site generator written in &lt;a href=&#34;http://golang.org&#34;&gt;Go&lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;rsquo;s incredibly fast and flexible, has a unique template engine, and writing themes is really easy, should the slew of available themes not be to your liking. I decided to use it because it lets me get rid of all the dependencies &lt;a href=&#34;http://jekyllrb.com/&#34;&gt;Jekyll&lt;/a&gt; came with, it had a comprehensive preview mechanism (&lt;code&gt;hugo server&lt;/code&gt;) and it allowed for a very narrow deployment pipeline to &lt;a href=&#34;http://pages.github.com&#34;&gt;GitHub Pages&lt;/a&gt;, where this site is hosted at. Coincidentally, this is also why it doesn&amp;rsquo;t offer TLS supports.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So without further ado, here are some instructions on how to get a Hugo site of your own, hosted on GitHub, for free!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;installing-hugo:536c0d2c3e7d958cd4c405a28a07ba8a&#34;&gt;Installing Hugo&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since Hugo is written in Go downloading and installing it can be as easy as pulling the individual binary and shoving it into the right place in your &lt;code&gt;$PATH&lt;/code&gt;. Just go to their &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/spf13/hugo/releases&#34;&gt;release website&lt;/a&gt; and take your pick. I used the &lt;code&gt;_amd64.deb&lt;/code&gt; since I&amp;rsquo;m running Ubuntu:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;$ wget https://github.com/spf13/hugo/releases/download/v0.13/hugo_0.13_amd64.deb
$ dpkg -i hugo_0.13_amd64.deb
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This will install &lt;code&gt;hugo&lt;/code&gt; to &lt;code&gt;/usr/bin&lt;/code&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;$ dpkg -L hugo
/usr/bin/hugo
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Obviously, you can also pull down the sources (via git or by downloading the zip file) and compile your own binary. &lt;a href=&#34;http://gohugo.io/overview/installing#installing-from-source&#34;&gt;There are detailed instructions on Hugo&amp;rsquo;s website&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;creating-your-new-hugo-site:536c0d2c3e7d958cd4c405a28a07ba8a&#34;&gt;Creating your new Hugo site&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To set up the Hugo scaffolding for your new site all you need to run is:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;$ hugo new site &amp;lt;path&amp;gt;
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now your directory in &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;path&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; should look something like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;$ ls
archetypes  config.toml  content  data  layouts  static
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hugo uses &lt;code&gt;toml&lt;/code&gt; as its configuration syntax by default. However, you can also use &lt;code&gt;yaml&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;json&lt;/code&gt; if you prefer either of those. The few directories carry a certain significance since taxonomy in Hugo is based on its directory structure:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://gohugo.io/content/archetypes/&#34;&gt;archetypes&lt;/a&gt;: This contains the default definitions for new content. You can add things like &lt;code&gt;tags&lt;/code&gt; or &lt;code&gt;categories&lt;/code&gt; here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://gohugo.io/content/organization/&#34;&gt;content&lt;/a&gt;: Here is where all your content goes. This means regular pages or, nested in directories, posts, categories etc.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://gohugo.io/extras/datafiles/&#34;&gt;data&lt;/a&gt;: You can store a poor man&amp;rsquo;s database in here and reference it right in your templates and pages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://gohugo.io/templates/overview/&#34;&gt;layouts&lt;/a&gt;: Relevant site layouts can be found in here. Usually, those would be provided by themes you&amp;rsquo;re using.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;static&lt;/code&gt;: Any content you don&amp;rsquo;t need to have touched by Hugo but want to use on your website goes in here.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, the &lt;code&gt;config.toml&lt;/code&gt; is where you main site configuration is stored. For my site it looks like this:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-toml&#34;&gt;# Your website URL
baseurl = &amp;quot;http://heiber.im&amp;quot;  
# The language you&#39;re using on it
languageCode = &amp;quot;en-us&amp;quot;  
# The main title of your website
title = &amp;quot;musings about silly things&amp;quot;  
# This should be here if you plan on using GitHub Pages
canonifyurls = true
# This is the editor Hugo calls upon when you run &amp;quot;hugo new post/something.md&amp;quot;
editor = &amp;quot;vim&amp;quot; 
# [...]
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can take a look at the current file &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/moritzheiber/huge-blog-website/blob/master/config.toml&#34;&gt;on GitHub&lt;/a&gt;. There are also a lot of theme dependent variables in there, which you can use pretty much anywhere in your layouts, theme definitions and content. &lt;a href=&#34;http://gohugo.io/templates/variables/&#34;&gt;There&amp;rsquo;s a whole section on template variables in the docs&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;grab-a-theme-you-like:536c0d2c3e7d958cd4c405a28a07ba8a&#34;&gt;Grab a theme you like&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is a &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/spf13/hugoThemes&#34;&gt;separate repository containing a lot of diverse and different themes&lt;/a&gt;. As of this moment there isn&amp;rsquo;t a comprehensive overview of the available themes accessible yet, however, there&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/spf13/hugoThemes/issues/35&#34;&gt;a ticket in GitHub which you can follow&lt;/a&gt; about finally getting a site up and running for exactly that purpose.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two ways of still giving them a try/taking a peek:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Each theme should contain a screenshot of it&amp;rsquo;s whole glory in the &lt;code&gt;images/&lt;/code&gt; directory. If it doesn&amp;rsquo;t consider filing an issue.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You can use the instructions mentioned in the &lt;code&gt;README.md&lt;/code&gt; to clone all of the available themes in the repository and then run &lt;code&gt;hugo server -t &amp;lt;theme-name&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; in order to try out each theme with your newly created blog&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;start-creating-content:536c0d2c3e7d958cd4c405a28a07ba8a&#34;&gt;Start creating content!&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now just run &lt;code&gt;hugo new post/new-first-post.md&lt;/code&gt; and have at it! If you want to see your changes appear incrementally you can run &lt;code&gt;hugo -w&lt;/code&gt; (&lt;code&gt;-w&lt;/code&gt; for &amp;ldquo;watch for changes&amp;rdquo;) in another window and navigate to &lt;a href=&#34;http://localhost:1313&#34;&gt;http://localhost:1313&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Especially with complicated markdown formatting this is a huge timesaver.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;push-it-to-the-web:536c0d2c3e7d958cd4c405a28a07ba8a&#34;&gt;Push it to the web&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After you&amp;rsquo;re done just run &lt;code&gt;hugo&lt;/code&gt; once in the blog&amp;rsquo;s directory. Mind your theme choice; you can use &lt;code&gt;-t &amp;lt;theme-name&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; if you haven&amp;rsquo;t added it to the configuration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Your statically created site is now ready for consumption in &lt;code&gt;public/&lt;/code&gt;. You can upload it anywhere you so desire. I personally host my website on GitHub Pages. There&amp;rsquo;s &lt;a href=&#34;http://gohugo.io/tutorials/github-pages-blog/&#34;&gt;a chapter on it in the Hugo docs&lt;/a&gt;. Just make sure to use the right method of branching/pushing, i.e. personal websites do not use a &lt;code&gt;gh-pages&lt;/code&gt; branch but rather &lt;code&gt;master&lt;/code&gt; directly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve created a &lt;code&gt;deploy.sh&lt;/code&gt; script which alleviates some of pain in the repetitive tasks you need to repeat in order to get your site onto GitHub Pages:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-bash&#34;&gt;#!/bin/bash

GIT_URL=&amp;quot;git@github.com:moritzheiber/moritzheiber.github.io.git&amp;quot;
GIT_BRANCH=&amp;quot;master&amp;quot;

echo -e &amp;quot;\033[0;32mDeploying updates to GitHub...\033[0m&amp;quot;

push_git () {
  msg=&amp;quot;Rebuilding site `date`&amp;quot;
  if [ $# -eq 1 ] ; then 
    msg=&amp;quot;$1&amp;quot;
  fi
  
  # Commit changes.
  git commit -m &amp;quot;$msg&amp;quot;

  # Push source and build repos.
  git push origin master
  git subtree push --prefix public ${GIT_URL} ${GIT_BRANCH}
}

# Build the project. 
hugo -t hyde-x

# Add changes to git.
git add --all
git diff --staged --stat

while true; do
    read -p &amp;quot;Do you wish to push these changes? &amp;quot; yn
    case $yn in
        [Yy]* ) push_git; break;;
        [Nn]* ) exit;;
        * ) echo &amp;quot;Please answer yes or no.&amp;quot;;;
    esac
done
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The script:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Builds the current state of the site using &lt;code&gt;hugo&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Adds all the changes to the git index and stages them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Gives you a brief overview of what they actually are.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Asks you to accept these changes.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Commits the changes, either using a provided messages (i.e. &lt;code&gt;./deploy.sh &amp;quot;your message here&amp;quot;&lt;/code&gt;) or a timestamped default.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pushes the changes to the main repository, also holding the &lt;code&gt;hugo&lt;/code&gt; codebase.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Pushes just the content in &lt;code&gt;public/&lt;/code&gt; to a separate repository, using the &lt;code&gt;master&lt;/code&gt; branch, so that it gets picked up by GitHub Pages.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That&amp;rsquo;s it. Your changes are now online.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;troubleshooting:536c0d2c3e7d958cd4c405a28a07ba8a&#34;&gt;Troubleshooting&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If you see a go backtrace at any point in time and you don&amp;rsquo;t happen to have any content in your blog yet it could be you&amp;rsquo;ve chosen a theme that relies on content to build certain parts of the site i.e. certain variables and/or content snippets. You should be fine once you&amp;rsquo;ve created more than or equal to one post/page.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;further-reading:536c0d2c3e7d958cd4c405a28a07ba8a&#34;&gt;Further reading&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hugo is very well documented, literally anything you desire can either by found &lt;a href=&#34;http://gohugo.io/overview/introduction/&#34;&gt;in the docs&lt;/a&gt; or on &lt;a href=&#34;http://discuss.gohugo.io/&#34;&gt;their buzzing forums&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;conclusion:536c0d2c3e7d958cd4c405a28a07ba8a&#34;&gt;Conclusion&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I couldn&amp;rsquo;t be happier with the setup at the moment. Right now, creating new posts is just about running &lt;code&gt;hugo new post/&amp;lt;post&amp;gt;.md&lt;/code&gt;, adding my content and then &lt;code&gt;./deploy.sh&lt;/code&gt;. After that it&amp;rsquo;s online. Two simple steps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s much easier and more seamless as it was before. I&amp;rsquo;m sorry to be moving away from such an accomplished project as Jekyll, but maintaining Jekyll and it&amp;rsquo;s dependencies just isn&amp;rsquo;t what I&amp;rsquo;m after and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.octopress.org&#34;&gt;Octopress 3.0&lt;/a&gt; isn&amp;rsquo;t ready yet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the time being, here&amp;rsquo;s to a bright future using &lt;a href=&#34;http://gohugo.io&#34;&gt;Hugo&lt;/a&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About me</title>
      <link>http://heiber.im/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2015 11:35:02 +0200</pubDate>
      <author>hello@heiber.im (Moritz Heiber)</author>
      <guid>http://heiber.im/about/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;figure class=&#34;about&#34;&gt;
    
        &lt;img src=&#34;http://heiber.im/images/moritz2.jpg&#34; /&gt;
    
    
    &lt;figcaption&gt;
        &lt;h4&gt;Copyright 2015, Martin Fowler&lt;/h4&gt;
        
    &lt;/figcaption&gt;
    
&lt;/figure&gt;

I&amp;rsquo;m Moritz Heiber and I work as DevOps Birth Assistant at &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.thoughtworks.com&#34;&gt;ThoughtWorks&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I used to work at ZenGuard as their VP of Engineering and at &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.babbel.com&#34;&gt;Babbel&lt;/a&gt; as their DevOps &amp;amp; Infrastructure Lead.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I also work as an independent consultant on all things computers and Internet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I love &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.ruby-lang.org&#34;&gt;Ruby&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.rust-lang.org&#34;&gt;Rust&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;https://golang.org&#34;&gt;Go&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&#34;http://linux.org&#34;&gt;Linux&lt;/a&gt; and all the things that come with them. I usually wrap my head around politics as well and I&amp;rsquo;m actively involved in promoting open source, diversity and the spirit behind them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like to give talks on DevOps, system operations and shiny things:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/moritzheiber/i-dont-care-for-what-you-did-last-summer&#34;&gt;I don&amp;rsquo;t care what you did last summer - Continuous Delivery and Immutable Servers&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/moritzheiber/codetalks-2014-fluentd-presentation&#34;&gt;Log the things! (German)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;stuff-i-use:6083a88ee3411b0d17ce02d738f69d47&#34;&gt;Stuff I use&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.i3wm.org&#34;&gt;i3wm&lt;/a&gt;: Exceptionally simple and versatile &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Tiling_window_manager&#34;&gt;tiling window manager&lt;/a&gt;. Beware: Once you use it every other way of interacting with a graphical user interfaces will seem inferior.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;http://vim.org&#34;&gt;vim&lt;/a&gt;: &lt;em&gt;The&lt;/em&gt; texteditor for pretty much anything. I might put up my &lt;code&gt;vimrc&lt;/code&gt; at some point in time.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/swanson/stringer&#34;&gt;stringer&lt;/a&gt;: Extremely easy to set up (literally takes you 10 minutes to get it running with Heroku. At no cost.) Rails rss feed aggregator. Has a beautiful web interface and implements the &lt;a href=&#34;http://feedafever.com&#34;&gt;Fever&lt;/a&gt; API specifications (for using &lt;a href=&#34;http://reederapp.com&#34;&gt;Reeder&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&#34;http://twentyfivesquares.com/press/&#34;&gt;Press&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dynamics DNS with pfSense and Route53</title>
      <link>http://heiber.im/post/dynamics-dns-with-pfsense-and-route53/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2014 12:17:36 +0100</pubDate>
      <author>hello@heiber.im (Moritz Heiber)</author>
      <guid>http://heiber.im/post/dynamics-dns-with-pfsense-and-route53/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;The quite excellent &lt;a href=&#34;https://pfsense.org&#34;&gt;pfSense&lt;/a&gt; comes with a &lt;a href=&#34;http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dynamic_DNS&#34;&gt;dynamic DNS&lt;/a&gt; plugin for &lt;a href=&#34;http://aws.amazon.com/route53/&#34;&gt;Amazon&amp;rsquo;s Route53 DNS management service&lt;/a&gt;. However, there is little to no documentation provided on how to set it up properly and especially about setting up the &lt;a href=&#34;http://aws.amazon.com/iam/&#34;&gt;relevant IAM access policies&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So I went to the &lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/pfsense/&#34;&gt;pfSense repository on GitHub&lt;/a&gt; and browsed the code in order to find out how much access the plugin needed in order to do its deed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As it turns out: not much. The following IAM policy will grant the plugin the required permissions to access Route53 on your behalf:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code&gt;{
  &amp;quot;Statement&amp;quot;:[
    {
      &amp;quot;Effect&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;Allow&amp;quot;,
      &amp;quot;Action&amp;quot;:[
        &amp;quot;route53:ChangeResourceRecordSets&amp;quot;,
        &amp;quot;route53:ListResourceRecordSets&amp;quot;
      ],
     &amp;quot;Resource&amp;quot;:&amp;quot;arn:aws:route53:::hostedzone/&amp;lt;your-hosted-zone-id&amp;gt;&amp;quot;
    }
  ]
}
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Notice the &lt;code&gt;&amp;lt;your-hosted-zone-id&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; which you need to exchange for the ID your zone has been assigned to within Route53.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What the dynamics DNS module within pfSense actually does:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Connect to the AWS API and look up all the records within the zone you configured&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Determines whether there is a record by the name you entered

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If there is it deletes the record and adds it back with the new IP address attached to it.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;em&gt;Note: This is also why it is very wise to chose a very low (&amp;lt;= 60 seconds) TTL for your dynamic DNS record&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If there isn&amp;rsquo;t it creates a new record and attaches the IP address to it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Saves the IP address it just set within Route53 to a file within the pfSense environment to make sure it doesn&amp;rsquo;t update the same record twice

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The IP either gets updated when the locally recorded IP address doesn&amp;rsquo;t match the record on Route53 or every 25 days&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After that the A record should get updated automatically each time the IP changes on the associated interface.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>