<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on musings about silly things</title>
    <link>https://heiber.im/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on musings about silly things</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <managingEditor>hello@heiber.im (Moritz Heiber)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>hello@heiber.im (Moritz Heiber)</webMaster>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Mar 2019 13:11:52 +0100</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://heiber.im/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Git client configurations for multiple identities</title>
      <link>https://heiber.im/post/git-client-configurations-for-multiple-identities/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Mar 2019 13:11:52 +0100</pubDate>
      <author>hello@heiber.im (Moritz Heiber)</author>
      <guid>https://heiber.im/post/git-client-configurations-for-multiple-identities/</guid>
      <description>The bane of maintenance If you&amp;rsquo;re like me, you&amp;rsquo;re using your computer not just for work but also for your own personal projects and learning efforts. After all, why would you buy a completely separate machine just for the sake of maintaining two separate working environments, keeping them up-to-date and running while also constantly forgetting about where exactly you put that one file
.. was it your personal laptop?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Creating a good, secure Docker base image</title>
      <link>https://heiber.im/post/creating-a-solid-docker-base-image/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 23 Feb 2016 18:24:05 +0100</pubDate>
      <author>hello@heiber.im (Moritz Heiber)</author>
      <guid>https://heiber.im/post/creating-a-solid-docker-base-image/</guid>
      <description>tl;dr: Build small, efficient images, use Alpine Linux as your foundation, build from there, add glibc if necessary, remove static/generated files and documentation, never run more than one process per container and use verified, trustworthy sources.
The premise When I first started using Docker, everyone kept raving about how easy and intuitive it was to use, how incredibly well it handled itself and how much time everyone was saving because of it.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>My thoughts on the Fitbit One</title>
      <link>https://heiber.im/post/my_thoughts_on_the_fitbit_one/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 11 Jun 2015 07:55:54 +0200</pubDate>
      <author>hello@heiber.im (Moritz Heiber)</author>
      <guid>https://heiber.im/post/my_thoughts_on_the_fitbit_one/</guid>
      <description>Like pretty much anyone interested in technology I was curious from the very beginning what body or fitness trackers can provide of value to our every day lives at this point in time. The ability to accurately judge your level of fitness and what to do about staying healthy is something I&amp;rsquo;d truly appreciate. I&amp;rsquo;ve been struggling with my body weight since I was a small child and still struggling with staying healthy, positive and depression free to this very date.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Switching to Hugo</title>
      <link>https://heiber.im/post/switching-to-hugo/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 10 May 2015 20:12:10 +0200</pubDate>
      <author>hello@heiber.im (Moritz Heiber)</author>
      <guid>https://heiber.im/post/switching-to-hugo/</guid>
      <description>Hugo is a static site generator written in Go. It&amp;rsquo;s incredibly fast and flexible, has a unique template engine, and writing themes is really easy, should the slew of available themes not be to your liking. I decided to use it because it lets me get rid of all the dependencies Jekyll came with, it had a comprehensive preview mechanism (hugo server) and it allowed for a very narrow deployment pipeline to GitHub Pages, where this site is hosted at.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dynamics DNS with pfSense and Route53</title>
      <link>https://heiber.im/post/dynamics-dns-with-pfsense-and-route53/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2014 12:17:36 +0100</pubDate>
      <author>hello@heiber.im (Moritz Heiber)</author>
      <guid>https://heiber.im/post/dynamics-dns-with-pfsense-and-route53/</guid>
      <description>The quite excellent pfSense comes with a dynamic DNS plugin for Amazon&amp;rsquo;s Route53 DNS management service. However, there is little to no documentation provided on how to set it up properly and especially about setting up the relevant IAM access policies.
So I went to the pfSense repository on GitHub and browsed the code in order to find out how much access the plugin needed in order to do its deed.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>